<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Guildhall-Chappel Decemb. 24, 1682 before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor &amp;c. by John James.</title>
            <author>James, John, b. 1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J428</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28735</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10750048</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10750048</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45644</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46627)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45644)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1405:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Guildhall-Chappel Decemb. 24, 1682 before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor &amp;c. by John James.</title>
                  <author>James, John, b. 1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Chiswell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christmas sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:45644:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Prichard Mayor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cur. Special. tent. die Dominico <hi>vii<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </hi> die Januarii, <hi>1682.</hi> Anno<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Regis Caroli ſecundi Angliae, &amp;c. <hi>xxxiiii<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THis Court doth deſire Mr. <hi>James</hi> to print his Sermon lately preached at the <hi>Guildhall</hi>-Chappel before the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagstaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45644:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at <hi>Guildhall-Chappel, <hi>Decemb.</hi>
               </hi> 24. 1682. BEFORE The Right Honourable THE Lord Mayor, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By JOHN JAMES, M. A. Rector of <hi>Latimers</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell,</hi> at the Roſe and Crown in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:45644:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45644:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>Sir Will. Prichard</hi> Knight, LORD MAYOR of the City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the many that juſtly admire your Lordſhips Worth, and ſeriouſly bleſs God for the Happineſs of <hi>London,</hi> in that the management of the Affairs of ſo great a Body, next under our Soveraign Lord the King, is committed into the hands of a Perſon of ſuch known Integrity and eminent Loyalty, the Author of this Diſcourſe doth cheerfully and heartily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs himſelf to be one.</p>
            <p>That this Diſcourſe was acceptable to your Lordſhip when delivered in the Pulpit, I muſt needs impute to that Candour and Goodneſs which ſeems innate and connatural to your Lordſhips diſpoſition, as is readily acknowledged by all that have but the leaſt knowledge of your Lordſhips Wiſdom and Prudence, ſo conſpicuous in the good conduct and auſpicious government of that great City: for though the Matter of it be incomparably great, yet the Manner of handling it falls infinitely ſhort of the worth and excellency
<pb facs="tcp:45644:3"/>of ſo divine a Subject, which ought to be highly eſteemed by all Chriſtians, and had in everlaſting remembrance by the Sons of Men.</p>
            <p>For 'twas a deſigne highly becoming the Son of God, to oppoſe the Devil, that grand Enemy of all Goodneſs, and to confront the powers of Darkneſs; to deliver Men from the dominion of Sin, and to ſecure them from the Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Almighty God. Indeed, a deſigne of this nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a Perſon of ſuch excellent and extraordinary Worth, ſuch divine Wiſdom, and infinite Power, ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Holineſs, and Almighty Goodneſs, to deſtroy the Works of the Devil, and to bring everlaſting Righteouſneſs into the World.</p>
            <p>And if the World had not been ſtrangely infatuated when the Son of God became Man, neither the <hi>Jews</hi> would have required a Signe, nor the <hi>Greeks</hi> ſought after Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, when he did ſo miraculouſly manifeſt his power to the ruine and deſtruction of the Devil, the moſt malicious and implacable Enemy of Mankind; whoſe inſulting Tyranny was far more ſevere and arbitrary over the <hi>Jews,</hi> than the cruelleſt oppoſition of the Roman Empire; and his Policy infinitely above the Philoſophical Wits and Reaſonings of the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> that if the one had not truſted too much to their humane Wiſdom, and the other longed too affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately for a temporal deliverance, and a ſecular happineſs, they muſt needs have celebrated the Nativity of the Son of God with the moſt ſolemn Hallelujahs and Hoſanna's, have admired him as the great Power of God, and the Wiſdom of God, who was made Man, that he might become unto men Wiſdom, and Righteouſneſs, and Sanctification, and Redemption.</p>
            <p>But the Men of this Generation are moſt of all without excuſe, that believe him to be the Son of God, and his
<pb facs="tcp:45644:3"/>coming into the World on purpoſe to deſtroy the Works of the Devil, and to take away the Sins of the World, and ſhall yet remain in ſlavery and ſubjection to the God of this World; and ſo do deſpite to the Holy One of God, and deny the Lord that bought them.</p>
            <p>I hope therefore no eye will look with envy upon this Diſcourſe, wherein no Diſpute is commenced, no Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie promoted, but with the great Impoſtor and deceiver of Souls; againſt whom every Chriſtian ought to employ his utmoſt knowledge and skill, and exert his greateſt vigour and zeal, being by the ſolemnity of an Oath, the Sacrament of Baptiſm, engaged thereto.</p>
            <p>And ſince this was the grand deſigne of Chriſt's coming into the World, I conceived an Argument of this nature very proper and ſeaſonable at this time, wherein we were to celebrate the Nativity of Chriſt, the Incarnation of the Son of God.</p>
            <p>And becauſe your Lordſhip hath commanded that this Diſcourſe, whatever it be, ſhould become publick (which elſe had remained as private as the Author) as I have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver eſteemed Obedience the beſt Sacrifice, and a ready ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the pleaſure of our Governours in all things law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, a moſt excellent Duty, and extreamly becoming all Chriſtian Profeſſors; ſo in compliance with your Lordſhips Command, it is now ſent forth into the World: and I hope, under the Patronage of ſo honourable a Perſon, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with the like kindneſs and good affection, as it was by your Lordſhip.</p>
            <p>And God grant that by the influence of his Grace it may be ſome way uſeful to thoſe that read it, to carry on that great end and deſigne for which it is intended; I mean, to encourage men againſt the Wiles and Temptations of the Devil; and to perſwade them to the works of Righteouſneſs
<pb facs="tcp:45644:4"/>and Goodneſs, of Piety and Devotion, of Juſtice and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, of Humility and Obedience, of Sobriety and Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p>God Almighty direct and aſſist your Lordſhip in the management of thoſe great Affairs committed to your charge, and continue you long in that famous City, to the Glory of his Name, the Credit of true Religion, the Honour of our Soveraign, and the happineſs of the People at preſent under your Government; that you may reap in this World ſatisfaction of Mind in the diſcharge of a good Conſcience; and in the World to come, everlaſting Life: Which is the hearty Prayer of him who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Jan. <hi>1. 1682/1.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhip's Very humble and moſt Obedient Servant,</hi> John James.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45644:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the Lord Mayor, &amp;c. Decemb. 24. 1682.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 JOH. 3.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For this purpoſe the Son of God was manifeſted, that he might deſtroy the works of the devil.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>NO ſooner were the Apoſtate Angels baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Court of Heaven, and by the juſt Judgment of God caſt into the <hi>bottomleſs Pit</hi> to undergo <hi>the vengeance of eternal fire,</hi> but the ſenſe of their torments exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperated their malice, and cauſed them to envy the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Man; which ſtayed not long within the breaſts of thoſe accurſed Spirits, but like a ſudden and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Floud that overflows its banks, and breaks down
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45644:5"/>all reſiſtance, they were reſtleſs in contriving the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of their fellow-creatures, and active as the flames of fire, till they had accompliſht this their horrid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne in tempting Man to apoſtatize from his Maker, that his Poſterity might become obnoxious to the ſame <hi>everlaſting fire, prepared for the devil and his Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſuch was the unwearied activity, together with the ſubtilty of that cunning Serpent, that his helliſh Plot ſoon took effect, in ſeducing our firſt Parents to hearken too attentively to his Enchantments, and through his treacherous ſuggeſtions, to queſtion the truth of what God had ſpoken, and ſoon after to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late what he had commanded. And when this firſt Stratagem too fatally ſucceeded in the world, and to the ruine of man directly anſwered the deſigne and expectation of the Devil, it inſpired a new life into that old Serpent, and encouraged him with the greater vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour to range up and down the world, <hi>ſeeking whom he might devour</hi> and deſtroy; that he hath long ſince uſurpt a principality and dominion over the Souls of men, and to this day continues <hi>the Prince of the power of the Air,</hi> nay, <hi>the God of this World, working in the Children of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience,</hi> and <hi>leading them captive at his will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the All-compaſſionate God pitying the Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackt condition of Man, did not, as in juſtice he might, totally abhor, and eternally reject him: for ſince by his fall he had diveſted himſelf of his primitive Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, proved a Rebel to his Lord and Maker, liſted himſelf into the ſervice of the Devil, and ſo ſtood at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen defiance with Heaven it ſelf; God Almighty, by the moſt ſignal inſtance of Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs, hath at once manifeſted his unſpeakable Love to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and his implacable Enmity to thoſe accurſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45644:5"/>by ſending his Son into the World, as the Captain of man's Salvation; who ſolemnly proclaimed open War with the Devil, bid defiance to him at his entrance into the World, and by Almighty power will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his aſpiring Pride and deſperate Malice, reſcue men from the hands of that <hi>roaring Lion,</hi> and ſo at once demoliſh his uſurped Kingdom, and deſtroy his works from off the face of the Earth.</p>
            <p>All which, as it was repreſented to man immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after his fall, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. that <hi>the Seed of the woman ſhould bruiſe the Serpents head,</hi> and that Promiſe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently renewed in ſucceeding Ages: ſo in the <hi>fulneſs of time</hi> it was happily begun by the Incarnation of the Son of God, who came to deliver men from the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Devil, to inveſt them with the liberty of the Sons of God, and to bring <hi>everlaſting Righteouſneſs</hi> into the World; is ſtill continued by his prevalency over the Devil, in confronting his Power, reſtraining his Malice, weakening his Intereſt in the World, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſing thoſe evil Spirits from the heart of man; and, when <hi>time ſhall be no more,</hi> ſhall be perfectly accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, to the eternal horrour, confuſion and amazement of the <hi>Devil and his Angels.</hi> Which is the juſt deſigne and proper import of theſe words: <hi>For this purpoſe the Son of God was manifeſted, that he might deſtroy the works of the Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the <hi>works of the Devil</hi> is here meant all manner of ſin, <hi>v.</hi> 5. for as he was the firſt Author, ſo he is the continual Promoter of that Corruption which reſides in the breaſt of men, and that Impiety which reigns in the World. So that all ſin, of what nature or quality ſoever it be, is the Brat and Off-ſpring of that diabolical Spirit, the proper effect of his ſpleen and malice to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45644:6"/>mankind, and, in the expreſſion of our Apoſtle, <hi>the works of the Devil:</hi> for, <hi>he that committeth ſin, is of the Devil; for the Devil ſinn'd from the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Son of God</hi> is the ſecond perſon in the bleſſed Trinity, God coequal and coeternal with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt. Who was <hi>manifeſt in the fleſh,</hi> became man, <hi>dwelt among us,</hi> and died for us, <hi>that he might deſtroy the works of the Devil:</hi> i. e. to <hi>teach and enable men to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Son of God was thus <hi>manifeſt to deſtroy the works of the Devil,</hi> will moſt evidently appear from the conſideration of three very material inſtances.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That the Son of God hath uſed thoſe means, and taken that courſe, which does directly tend, and is abundantly able to ſubvert the power of the Devil.</item>
               <item>2. That in many remarkable inſtances he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſupplanted his Power in the World.</item>
               <item>3. That he will certainly obtain a moſt perfect Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over the Devil, before he reſigne up his Commiſſion to his Father.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. The Son of God hath uſed thoſe means, and taken that courſe which does directly tend, and is abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to ſubvert the power of the Devil. The truth of which Propoſition will be fully illuſtrated, from the conſideration of four things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the whole courſe and frame of his Life, whilſt manifeſt in the World; wherein he was ſo far from complying with, that he did utterly diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45644:6"/>the works of the Devil. The Generation of Mankind, according to the courſe of Nature, is too much attended with the heat of Luſt, and the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Original Corruption into the Embryo at its firſt conception: therefore the ever-bleſſed Jeſus coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, was conceived by a moſt ſtupendous and admirable manner; the power of the Holy Ghoſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſhadowing a pure Virgin, that ſhe became great with Child of the Son of God; and when the number of her months were accompliſhed, ſhe brought him forth into the World as richly adorned with divine and ſupernatural Graces, as he was poor in reſpect of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance. When his Infancy was paſt, that he came to the uſe of Reaſon and Underſtanding, a time wherein other men begin to diſcover the natural cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of their hearts, by their actual rebellion againſt God, the <hi>Son of God</hi> (truly ſo called from his divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like nature and holy life, as well as his miraculous and happy birth) begins his Converſation with an even and a regular Piety, free from thoſe ſinful paſſions, though attended with the natural infirmities which mankind labours under; and accordingly regulates them according to the Laws of Nature, and the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his heavenly Father. His Charity was truly Chriſtian and diffuſive, ſuch as extended to all orders and degrees of men. His meek and ſweet diſpoſition, with his humble and modeſt Spirit, ſuch as appears in Infants before they can diſcern between good and evil. His converſing with men was free and familiar, eaſie and unaffected. His dutiful reſpects toward his Friends and Relations, tranſcending that of the moſt ingenuous diſpoſition, though cultivated by the early advantages of a pious Education. Neither did he ſuffer his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45644:7"/>to decline, as ſome men do, when their years in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe; but as he multiplied days, and <hi>grew in ſtature, he increaſed in wiſdom and favour with God and man,</hi> Luke 2.52.</p>
            <p>He was careful to omit no duty, and ſo deſirous to give no offence; that where he might lawfully conform to the Cuſtoms of his Nation and Kindred, he did not with a moroſe and churliſh diſpoſition (like the men of our Age) depart from them, but with great freedom, and a cheerful ſpirit, comply with and conform to them: Witneſs his Circumciſion the eighth day, his being baptized by <hi>John,</hi> his paying Tribute, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But where the ſacred Bonds of Religion required and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his obedience, neither the violent aſſaults of Satan,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.22, 23</note> nor the courteous compellations of Friends, could conſtrain him to violate the deareſt Heaven. He e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed Obedience the beſt Sacrifice to his Father, and preferred the ſervice of God before the love and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his deareſt Friends;<note place="margin">Heb. 10.7.</note> chuſing rather to die, than to ſin againſt God.</p>
            <p>For when his Enemies were moſt furiouſly inraged againſt him, and conſulted to put him to death, he makes no evaſion, nor unjuſt excuſes; he denies not the truth, nor diſtruſts his Father; but committing his Caſe to the providence of God,<note place="margin">Mat. c. 26. c. 29.</note> he meekly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures their affronts and injuries; and when their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice was ſo great as to put him to death, he patiently bears their indignation, their fury, and their wrath, like a good man and a glorious Martyr, praying for his Enemies till he gave up the Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Behold here a Mirrour of Piety, the Wonder of the world for his Devotion and Charity! Was there any action of his life, or the leaſt circumſtance attending his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45644:7"/>actions, that might juſtly bear the charge of ſin? None certainly: for from his birth to his death, he was a moſt virulent Enemy to that wicked One, and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect hater of his works. The Devils themſelves confeſs he was <hi>the holy One of God:</hi> His moſt malicious Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies could not but ſay he <hi>did all things well:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>Pilate</hi> that ſate in Judgment upon him, could <hi>find no evil in him;</hi> and therefore according to his Wife's admonition,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.19, 23, 24.</note> proclaims him before a full Aſſembly of Scribes and Elders, to be <hi>a juſt perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that his whole Life was but one continued Series of actions perfectly deſigned againſt that wicked One. His Baptiſm was his ſolemn inauguration into this Office. His Converſation the moſt plain and eaſie,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.28, 29.</note> the moſt full and comprehenſive, the moſt encouraging and authentick Pattern for his Followers to imitate in their Chriſtian courſe of life, in defiance to that grand Impoſtor; that while they behold him as <hi>the Captain of their Salvation,</hi> deſpiſing the World, confronting the Devil, bearing Afflictions with patience, Perſecutions with cheerfulneſs, reſiſting and overcoming Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, forgiving and loving his Enemies, willing to live ſo long as God pleaſed, yet ready to die the moſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious accurſed death, ſince it was the determinate counſel of God: Whilſt his Diſciples thus conſider his regular Piety, his undaunted Courage, they may learn to <hi>do likewiſe;</hi> and in oppoſition to the Prince of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, be encouraged to do, to ſuffer, and to be, whatever God ſhall be pleaſed to call them to.</p>
            <p>'Twas <hi>Plato</hi>'s opinion, as <hi>Tully</hi> reports, that if Vertue could but admit herſelf to view, ſhe would appear ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable in the eyes of all men, that Vice in the moſt coſtly dreſs and gorgeous array would appear moſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45644:8"/>contemptible and bare, if compared with her. If in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated Vertue in the Philoſophers judgment would be ſo attractive of mens affections, certainly the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted innocency of an incarnate Deity ſhould be much more powerful to invite and perſwade his Followers to the love and practice of Piety and Goodneſs, than the former conceit would be to engage men to the love and practice of Vertue: So that if men would conſider that grand Exemplar of Piety, <hi>the life of the holy Jeſus,</hi> his Example muſt needs inſpirit their minds with the moſt active diligence, &amp; undaunted courage, to fight manfully under his Banner,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 12.1, 2, 3.</note> as <hi>the Captain of their Salvation,</hi> againſt the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, to <hi>run with patience the race that is ſet before them,</hi> and to continue in that ſpiritual Combat his faithful Servants and Souldiers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their lifes end.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From ſome remarkable actions of his Life, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the bitter paſſions of his Death, whereby he hath given a fatal blow to the power and deſignes of the Devil. The Son of God is not to be conſidered onely as a meer man, though juſt and innocent, but in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence alſo to that grand undertaking, [The Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of the World from its ſlavery to Sin and ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Satan], the Saviour of the World, the Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of Mankind: His very Birth ſtruck a terrour to thoſe evil Spirits; his Life ſhone with ſo glorious a light, that it confounded the Kingdom of Darkneſs: But the moſt ſignal Conqueſt he obtained over Death,<note place="margin">Eph 2.13, &amp;c.</note> and the Devil that had the power of it, was by his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious Death and powerful Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>For when the <hi>Jews</hi> had crucified the <hi>Lord of Life,</hi> and laid him full low, even in the duſt, that they began to triumph and applaud themſelves in their ſuppoſed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45644:8"/>Victory, the Devils alſo rejoyced, as if they had van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed the power of God. How miraculouſly did the Counſels of Heaven defeat the carnal policy of men, and the malicious deſignes of the Devil too! That death which they executed upon the <hi>Lord's Anointed,</hi> was converted to their own deſtruction, and, contrary to the Devils expectation, moſt happily proved the greateſt Engine to rout his Forces, and deſtroy his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. For can <hi>God die?</hi> or <hi>his holy One ſee corruption?</hi> No; the price of man's Redemption being paid by the Sufferings of the Son of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.9, 10</note> he broke through the powers of the Grave; and in deſpight of the Devil, Hell, and Death, aroſe a mighty Conquerour over them all; and as a Trophey of Victory, <hi>led captivity captive,</hi> and treated them as he pleaſed: And when he had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſufficient demonſtration of his Reſurrection,<note place="margin">Acts 1.9.</note> he aſcended gloriouſly into Heaven, from whence imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately he ſent down the Holy Ghoſt upon his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and prevalently interceding with his Father, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived power and authority to demoliſh the Kingdom of Satan,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.19, 20, 21, 22.</note> and by delivering men from his inſulting Tyranny, to conſtitute a Kingdom of his own; and to preſerve and keep it from the furious aſſaults of the Devil, by the power of his Providence, and the conduct of his Spirit. And now he is ſet down at the right hand of God, he continueth for ever; and having an unchangeable Prieſthood, is able to <hi>ſave</hi> his Church and People <hi>to the utmoſt, ſeeing he ever liveth to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for them,</hi> Heb. 7.24, 25. By which, and other ſuch remarkable paſſages, preceding, accompanying, and following his death, he hath obtained a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble intereſt in the very Forts and Dwellings of the Prince of this World, by <hi>turning many ſouls from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45644:9"/>to light, and from the power of Satan unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. From the grand intent and deſigne of his Doctrine, which is moſt aptly contrived to deſtroy the works of the Devil, to deliver men from the power and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſin, and to direct and encourage them to Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and true Holineſs. For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> The Chriſtian Religion delivers the ſtricteſt Precepts for the rule of good living, with the greateſt Majeſty and Authority conceivable. In general, it commands men <hi>to love the Lord their God with all their heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22.37, 38, 39.</note> 
               <hi>and with all their ſoul, and with all their mind, and their neighbours as themſelves;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.12.</note> to <hi>do as they would be done unto;</hi> to reject the Devil, and deſpiſe the World: to avoid every <hi>occaſion of ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 4.7. 1 Joh. 2.15. 1. Theſſ. 5.22.</note> and <hi>appearance of evil;</hi> and <hi>whatever things are true, whatever things are honeſt, whatever things are juſt, whatever things are pure, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever things are lovely, whatever things are of good report; if there be any vertue, and if there be any praiſe, ſeriouſly to think of theſe things,</hi> and faithfully to do them, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8, 9.</p>
            <p>More particularly,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.3. 1 Tim. 6.15, 16</note> it requires men to acknowledge one God the Creator and Governours of the World, to conceive him as an infinite and incomprehenſible Being, to teſtifie the inward reverence and devotion of their hearts,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1, 2.</note> by the moſt ready and univerſal obedience to his Will; to love him for his Goodneſs; to ſtand in awe of his Juſtice and his Power;<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.8. Mat. 10.28. Mat. 6.25. 1 Theſſ. 5.18. Joh. 4.24.</note> to depend upon his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for their protection, and to expreſs their thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs for the receipt of his Mercies: to be ſerious in all parts of his Worſhip; to live always as in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; and to manifeſt their reſpect to God, by their reverend behaviour to every thing that is appropriate to his ſervice, or participates of his nature: Faithfully
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45644:9"/>to believe all divine Revelations; humbly to ſubmit to all the diſpenſations of his Providence, and ſincerely to obſerve all the manifeſtations of his Will and Pleaſure: To believe on the Son of God as the Saviour of the World, the great Doctor and Governour of the Church,<note place="margin">Mat. 1.21. Jam. 4.12. 1 Tim. 2.5.</note> and the alone <hi>Mediator between God Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It preſcribes the particular Offices, engaging men to a due regulation of all their thoughts, words, and deeds, that do immediately reſpect their own perſons.<note place="margin">Luke 21.34.</note> It di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects them to Temperance and Moderation in eating and drinking, in ſleeping and recreation; to Chaſtity and Purity both in the married and unmarried eſtate; to Humility and Modeſty in the diſpoſition and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of men:<note place="margin">Acts 24.16.</note> To reſtrain every unruly Paſſion within the bounds of Reaſon, and to regulate every the moſt lawful Affection according to the rules of Religion: To guide and manage their Behaviour with ſobriety and underſtanding, and to order their Diſcourſe with gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and diſcretion.</p>
            <p>It lays down alſo the moſt excellent Rules of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Juſtice toward their Neighbours, obliging every man to the greateſt Sincerity, Uprightneſs, and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity to each other;<note place="margin">Mat. 5.23, 24, 25. Rom. 13.7.</note> to an univerſal Innocence and Harmleſneſs in all actions; to make Compenſation where Offences have been committed; to carry a due Reſpect and Reverence, proper to the ſeveral Orders and Degrees of men; to obſerve all the poſitive Acts of Juſtice, diſtributive and commutative, according to the Offices of that Calling wherein divine Providence hath diſpoſed man's Station; and to obſerve all the duties of Love and Charity, which the neceſſities of others require,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> and the abilities of men do qualifie them for. In a word, the Chriſtian Profeſſion is ſo pure, ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45644:10"/>undefiled a Religion, that it prohibits the leaſt impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and gives no licenſe to the ſmalleſt ſin: for, <hi>the grace of God that bringeth ſalvation, hath appeared to all men, teaching us, that denying ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world; looking for that bleſſed hope, and the glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.11, 12, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>and purifie unto himſelf a peculiar people, zealous of good works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> It propounds the moſt convincing Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to encourage men againſt the Wiles and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations of the Devil, and to perſwade them to the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and conſtant practice of Vertue and Goodneſs. It threatens the Wicked with the Wrath and Indignation of God at preſent; and promiſeth to the Vertuous and Good, the Providence of God, as his infinite Wiſdom ſhall judge moſt expedient for them. But becauſe it is manifeſt God doth not call Mankind to an account in this World, nor deal with them in ſtrict Juſtice according to their deſerts, (for his external Diſpenſations are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry promiſcuous both to the Good and Bad) therefore the Goſpel doth ſeriouſly preſent to the conſideration of men, an infallible certainty of a Judgment to come, when God ſhall render to every man according to his works,<note place="margin">Acts 17.31. 2 Pet. 3.10. 2 Theſſ. 1.7. Mat. 25.30. <hi>ad fin.</hi>
               </note> 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 5.10. It informs us of the nature of the Judge, the dreadful preparation for his coming to Judgment, the terrible appearance of his Majeſty, the great proceedings of that day, and the irreverſible Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence paſt upon all concerned in it; that we may be confidently aſſured there are Rewards in ſtore for every man, that <hi>the wickedneſs of the wicked ſhall be upon him, and the righteouſneſs of the righteous ſhall be upon him.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:45644:10"/>It repreſents the greateſt fulneſs and exuberancy of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love:<note place="margin">Rom. 2.7, 8, 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>Life and Immortality</hi> to the Vertuous and Good; but the utmoſt ſeverity of divine Juſtice, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and Wrath, Tribulation and Anguiſh,</hi> to the Vicious and Bad.</p>
            <p>It aſſures to all that live according to the Rules of that holy Inſtitution, eternal and ſolid Bliſs both in Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soul: that the one, <hi>which was corruptible, ſhall put on incorruption; which was ſown in diſhonour, ſhall be raiſed in glory; which was ſown in weakneſs, ſhall be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in power,</hi> 2 Cor. 15.42, 43. And the faculties of the other ſo eminently transformed, that the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which now ſeeth the moſt perſpicuous things but darkly and through a Glaſs, ſhall be endued with the greateſt meaſure of knowledge, and entertained with the cleareſt ſight of the divine nature, to behold with infinite ſatisfaction the glorious attributes of God, and the wonderful Counſels and effects of them all, in his works of Providence toward his ſeveral Creatures. The Will and Affections ſhall be perfectly transformed into the divine likeneſs; that Anger, Envy, Hatred, and ſuch troubleſome Paſſions, ſhall be utterly aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Deſire ſhall be ſped into Fruition, and Hope ſhall be ſwallowed up in Victory; and thoſe delightful and raviſhing affections of Love and Joy, ſhall ſurvive and remain to the eternal conſolation of Soul and Body.</p>
            <p>But it threatens the <hi>Wicked</hi> that they <hi>ſhall be turned into hell, and all the people that forget God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 9.24 26.</note> where are Flames ſo quick and ſcorching, that they ſhall ſeize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Soul and Body; Torments that ſhall always be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, never ending; which the damned themſelves by their Malice ſhall increaſe, and by the gnaſhing of their Teeth ſhall help to be their own Executioners.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45644:11"/>So that thoſe who comply with the Wiles and Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Devil, muſt <hi>expect a certain fearful looking for of judgment, and fiery indignation which ſhall devour them,</hi> Heb. 10.27. but thoſe who reſiſt that evil Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſeriouſly renounce his works, may expect that glorious <hi>recompence of reward which God hath prepared for thoſe that love and ſerve him,</hi> Heb. 11.39, 40.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly.</hi> To this purpoſe, that divine Oeconomy, which according to the Sanctions of the Goſpel is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred in the Chriſtian Church, was inſtituted by the Son of God. That the Miniſters of the Goſpel, as opportunity ſerves, and neceſſity requires, adminiſter the ſacred Rites of the Chriſtian Religion in the Church of God,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> by baptizing ſuch as are duly diſpoſed for that ſolemn Ordinance; that thereby they may be liſted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſervice of Chriſt, and by that religious Sacrament be obliged to fight manfully under his Banner againſt the World,<note place="margin">Luke 22.19, 20</note> the Fleſh, and the Devil: And diſtribute the Holy Communion to thoſe pious and humble Souls, that are religiouſly diſpoſed to celebrate the honour of God in that ſacred Inſtitution; that they may be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to <hi>quench the fiery darts of the devil,</hi> and <hi>have grace to ſerve God acceptably with reverence and godly fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To them 'tis commanded to ſolemnize the Worſhip of God in publick,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.12, 13 1 Tim. 2.1, 2.</note> either as Prieſts to wait at the Altar of the Lord, to intercede with his Majeſty in the behalf of his people, and to preſent in their ſtead Prayers and Supplications, and Thankſgivings to him; or as Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors to treat with the People in the buſineſs of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.20. 2 Cor. 5.20.</note> and reveal the Will of God unto them; to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain and confirm to their Underſtandings the Principles of Chriſtianity, to repreſent to their Judgment and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45644:11"/>Reaſon, the vileneſs of ſin, and the reaſonableneſs of Gods ſervice; that men may be reclaimed from their ſinful and wicked ways, and become <hi>a living ſacrifice, holy and acceptable unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when ſinners are obſtinate and hard to be entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Cenſures of the Church are put into their hands, to exerciſe the power of the Keys in puniſhing the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinacious, and caſting them out of the Church, that they may be brought to a juſt and lively apprehenſion of their ſins; and from the Judgment of God executed upon them by his Miniſters in the Church, be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to reform and amend their lives, that they may not fall into the hands of divine Juſtice in the World to come; and ſo upon ſufficient Evidence of their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, receive Abſolution, be diſſolved from the Bonds of Satan, and admitted into the boſome of the Church again. For this power our Lord and Maſter commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Apoſtles, and in them to the ſucceeding Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the Church, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Whatſoever ye ſhall bind on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven; and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye ſhall looſe on earth, ſhall be looſed in heaven.</hi> Which Commiſſion was renewed again after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, when he breathed on them the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.22, 23.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the principal means delivered in the Goſpel, and inſtituted by the Son of God, to deliver men from the dominion of ſin and Satan; and thereby <hi>to deſtroy the works of the Devil,</hi> by taking men off from the love and practice of ſin.</p>
            <p n="4">4. From the miſſion and deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt into the World; where divine Inſpiration is in two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects very remarkable: to take away and the ſins of the World, and to promote the ſervice and honour of God.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:45644:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> By enduing the Son of God and his holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles with power from above, whereby they were ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to confirm and ratifie the truth of the Chriſtian Doctrine by the working of Miracles. If Chriſt had not <hi>done thoſe works which no other perſon did,</hi> he would not, for in truth he could not, have obliged mankind to believe and obey it: which is the proper import and meaning of our Saviour's expreſſion, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.24. 'Twas therefore extreamly neceſſary that he ſhould manifeſt the Divinity of his perſon, and confirm the truth of the Goſpel, by ſuch ſignal Teſtimonies as were uncontrola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: And ſuch was his infinite Wiſdom and Power, that while he was converſant among men, he gave the World all the ſatisfaction that was poſſible, that he came from God; when he wrought ſuch miraculous works as were never heard of from the beginning of the World, preſented them boldly to all Spectators, and committed the tryal of their reality to the teſt of their ſences; which was an infallible evidence that <hi>the ſpirit of the Lord was upon him,</hi> and the <hi>power of God had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowed him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9.14. Rom. 8.11.</note> But becauſe he was <hi>mightily declared to be the Son of God by his reſurrection from the dead,</hi> as <hi>through the eternal ſpirit he offered himſelf to God;</hi> ſo by the mighty aſſiſtance of the ſame holy Spirit, he aroſe again from the dead, and continues alive for ever.</p>
            <p>And becauſe he committed the promulgation of the Goſpel to his Apoſtles, whom he ſent as Embaſſadours to preach Salvation to the World, and exhort ſinners to be reconciled to God; the powers of the Holy Ghoſt was indiſpenſably requiſite to inform their Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings with the Mind of God, to reveal the ſacred My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Religion clearly to their apprehenſions, that they be aſſured of their heavenly Call to the divine Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45644:12"/>therefore they had apparitions of Angels, and received the Bath-col, voices from Heaven. So St. <hi>Paul</hi> by a moſt miraculous Light from Heaven, is ſtricken down to the Earth, and called to the Apoſtleſhip, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. Hereupon he became ſo ſerious and earneſt to aſſert both his Calling and Goſpel to deſcend from Heaven, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Paul an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, not of men, neither by men, but by Jeſus Chriſt, and God the Father.</hi> They had extatical Viſions; <hi>Peter</hi> was in a Trance, <hi>Paul</hi> wrapt up to the third Heavens: They had monitory Dreams and Impulſes from the Spirit; by all which, they had a full aſſurance of the Divinity of their Meſſage, and the truth of their Call to the Apoſtleſhip.</p>
            <p>But 'twas equally neceſſary, for the Conviction of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing World, that they ſhould confirm the divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of theſe things, by ſufficient external Arguments: therefore they were endued with the gift of Tongues, and the power of working Miracles; when according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of our Lord, the Holy Ghoſt deſcended from Heaven upon a full Aſſembly, as they were met together to ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the Worſhip of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. that they began to ſpeak with other Tongues, and to utter divers ſorts of Languages, inſomuch that their Auditors admired the marvelous works of God, when they heard the Servants of Chriſt ſpeaking e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one in their own Tongue. Thus they were qualified by an extraordinary Inſpiration, to teach all Nations, and to preach the Goſpel throughout the whole World. And as they had diverſity of Gifts, and different Adminiſtrations, ſo they were enabled by the power of the Holy Ghoſt to work Miracles,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> and in the Name of Chriſt to do even what they liſt. To them was given the power of healing all manner of Diſeaſes, the raiſing the Dead to life. But one great and ſignal Gift they received, which to the highth of admiration they manifeſted to the World; the frequent ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of the Spirit upon themſelves, the communicating of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45644:13"/>it to others by praying, preaching, and laying on of hands, whereby evil Spirits became ſubject to them, that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed over the Devil and his deluding Oracles, whoſe Tongues they ſilenc'd, whoſe Forgeries they diſcover'd, whoſe Favorites they ſtrangely and in a moment ſtruck dead, and reſtrained the malice and fury of Lucifer himſelf.</p>
            <p>Were theſe the effects of any other power than the Spirit of the Lord? Was it ever heard that a meer Mortal was able to do the like? to alter the courſe of Nature, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce effects directly contrary to the production of natural cauſes? Is it within the power of the Mighty? or can the Devils themſelves bring it to paſs? No: It requires an Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent arm; no leſs than that which created the World, and ſetled the particular Beings therein: to change their courſes, to alter their natures, to work not onely with ſlender and unlikely means, but without and againſt all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable methods, certainly none but the Spirit of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty can do thus. When therefore the power of working Miracles is the alone work of a Deity, and ſuch remarkable inſtances were plainly manifeſt by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, to diſcover the Divinity, and procure the belief of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; it's a plain Argument, that that extraordinary pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with which they were inveſted, was on purpoſe deſigned to diſcard the Devil, and confront his Power; becauſe that Doctrine which was confirmed by them, is directly contrary to the deſignes and projects of that evil Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> By its continual influence upon the Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and Wills of men, to enable them to reſiſt the Devil, and overcome his Temptations. Though the Doctrine of the Goſpel had ſuch an undeniable Evidence as the Power of Miracles, to aſcertain the truth and verity of it, that one would think no man, which believes the matter of fact, that ſuch miracles were wrought, ſhould doubt of the truth, or queſtion the divine Authority of the Chriſtian Religion, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45644:13"/>conſequently would ſoon reſigne up their Underſtanding to the obedience of Faith, to be governed by the Laws of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution: yet he that conſiders how little men regard the Authority of that divine Teſtimony, and conſider the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the Goſpel diſcovery, and how careleſs men are to be ſtrict and ſerious in their Converſations, and how ſoon debauched by the moſt eaſie Temptation, who profeſs to believe Jeſus Chriſt to be the Son of God, and aſſent to his Doctrine as infallibly true, will ſoon perceive the neceſſity of ſome ſupernatural aſſiſtance, to bring the hearts of men to the love, and their lives to the practice of all neceſſary truths contained therein, over and above that miraculous diffuſion at the firſt delivery and preaching of it.</p>
            <p>And bleſſed be the Name of God, ſuch is the large and plentiful effuſion of divine Grace now under the diſpenſation of the Goſpel, that 'tis always ready at hand to aſſiſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of men, in all religious purpoſes and holy undertakings, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26.16. And in ſeveral places of the Goſpel, the Spirit is promiſed to the devout and humble petitions of honeſt Chriſtians, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.23.26. So that the moſt degenerate Soul that does but ſeriouſly apply his mind to <hi>fear God and keep his Commandments,</hi> will find ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual aſſiſtance from the bleſſed ſpirit of Grace, as will ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him to mortifie his own Corruption, to quench the fiery darts of the Devil, to vanquiſh all oppoſitions in the way to Goodneſs, and with eaſe and pleaſure to do the Will of God.</p>
            <p>For this very purpoſe the Son of God intercedes with his Father, and preſents our Prayers to the Throne of Grace by vertue of his own interceſſion, that the Promiſe of the Holy Ghoſt may be continued to his Church to the end of the world, to ſanctifie the hearts of his People, and to fill their Souls with all thoſe graces that accompany Salvation; to enlighten the Underſtanding, to convince the Judgment, to awaken the Conſciences of men, that they may believe and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45644:14"/>conſider the great and weighty Principles of Religion, and be preſerved from all falſe Doctrine, Hereſies, and Schiſms: to preſs upon their conſideration the folly and unreaſonableneſs of ſin, with the dreadful conſequences of a wicked life; the excellency of true Religion and Goodneſs, with the bleſſed ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of a vertuous Converſation, that men may be perſwaded to <hi>depart from evil, and do good:</hi> to remove the obſtinacy and perverſeneſs that is natural to fallen man, that their Spirits may become pliable and ſubmiſſive to the providential dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of God, reſpective and obedient to the Laws and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of Heaven, and entirely devoted to his Will and Pleaſure: to confirm their Faith, increaſe their Integrity; to aſſiſt them againſt Temptations; to ſupport them with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence under afflictions; to compleat their Charity, to perfect their Repentance, and to enable them by Promiſes, Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Gifts, to ſuffer for the Lord Jeſus, and the profeſſion of the Goſpel, if called to it. All this and much more is the Promiſe of the Father, to purchaſe of the Son of God, and the gift of them both to give the holy Spirit to the Church, firſt to <hi>ſanctifie</hi> and make it good,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.22. 1 Theſſ. 5.23.</note> then to <hi>preſerve it ſpotleſs and unblamable to the coming of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the principal means invented by the Wiſdom of God to <hi>take away the ſins of the world, to deſtroy the works of the devil;</hi> and in infinite mercy preſented to mankind by his onely begotten Son, to <hi>deliver them from the power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and by <hi>turning them away from their iniquities, to tranſlate them into the kingdom of his dear Son.</hi> And what can the wit of man conceive, what doth the weakneſs of men want as far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther needful to promote and carry on this bleſſed and glorious deſigne? What could God have done more to ſubvert the power of the Devil, and to reconcile Mankind to himſelf?</p>
            <p>If he had raiſed up ſome mighty Prophet in the World, and furniſhed him with the Inſpiration of the Almighty, that he had ſpoken as one having Authority, and commended his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45644:14"/>Meſſage to us in the Name of the Lord; we ſhould certainly have received him in the Name of a Prophet: or if an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel had deſcended from Heaven, and appeared viſibly to us Mortals, and delivered his Embaſſage to us in a Seraphick manner, and backt it with Reaſons clear as his Angelical na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; we ſhould certainly have admired the goodneſs of God, and acknowledged our ſelves obliged to ſo gracious a Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. But that God himſelf ſhould deſcend from thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions above into this dark and diſmal World, become one like us, one of us, and ſo in a way agreeable to our humane capacities, deliver us the Records of Heaven, tell us the terms on which our Eternity depends, aſſure us upon his undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Veracity, that upon our obedience or diſobedience to them, Heaven or Hell, Life or Death are aſcertained to us; that he ſhould delineate to our very eyes in plain and legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Characters, the excellency of his Doctrine by the Piety and Innocency of his Life, and ſo recommend his Precepts to our practice by his own Example ſet before us; that he ſhould convince and aſſure us of the Divinity of his Perſon and Doctrine, by many and undeniable Miracles; that he ſhould ſeal the truth of what he delivered by his own bloud; offer up his Life a Sacrifice to death, to procure life to the ſinful World; that by his divine power he ſhould riſe out of the Grave, gloriouſly aſcend to Heaven, intercede with his Father on our behalf, and from thence ſend us <hi>another Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, even the ſpirit of Truth,</hi> which ſhould inform our minds with the knowledge of all neceſſary truths, and bring us to the love and practice of all Chriſtian Vertues and Graces: Certainly this method is abundantly able to <hi>deſtroy the works of the Devil,</hi> and the prevail with ſinners to lead godly and pious lives. Which will moſt evidently appear, if we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to conſider the ſecond Argument to illuſtrate the truth of the Apoſtles Aſſertion.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Son of God hath in many remarkable inſtances
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45644:15"/>already ſupplanted the Power of the Devil, in delivering ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Souls from the tyranny and dominion of that inſulting Enemy, notwithſtanding the great diſadvantages and diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements that the Chriſtian Religion hath met with in the World both from Jews and Gentiles, from the firſt plantation of the Goſpel until now.</p>
            <p>For though the Jews were <hi>circumciſed the eighth day,</hi> and in their Childhood kept in cruel bondage under their Parents and Maſters, who conſtrained them to learn the Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> and when they came to riper years, were taught by the <hi>Scribes and Phariſees,</hi> who <hi>ſate in Moſes Chair,</hi> that their Religion was eternal, and the Oeconomy thereof never to be altered; and therefore were bound to reject any perſon that ſhould broach any other Doctrine, to diſcard him from their Synagogues, to ſtop his mouth that he might not ſpeak, and their ears that they might not hear. And 'tis notorious that the Gentiles were no leſs fortified in their Heathen Rites, and ſuperſtitious Cuſtoms, every Nation having their reſpective Deities, whom they conſtantly adored and offered Sacrifice to; and ſome of them ſo careful to ſecure the honour of their Gods, and all under their Authority in their Idolatrous ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances, that as <hi>Melanchton</hi> notes in his Epiſtle to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the <hi>Romans,</hi> every <hi>Athenian</hi> made a Vow at his admiſſion to the Liberties and Franchiſes of the City, <hi>ſe pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare pro diis, ſolum, &amp; cum aliis,</hi> not onely to fight valiantly in the front of an Army, to defend and vindicate their Gods, but, like the Roman <hi>Scaeva,</hi> to withſtand whole Legions.</p>
            <p>Adde to all this, the Oppoſition that was to be expected without, the Scoffs and Jears that Chriſtians muſt expect from their Neighbours, the Cenſures of their Laws, and the diſpleaſure of their Governours; the meanneſs of Chriſt, and the unworthineſs of his Apoſtles, the poverty and weakneſs of them both; that they were utterly unable to ſupply the wants of their Diſciples, or defend them from the malice and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45644:15"/>cruelty of their Enemies. But above all, conſider the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of their hearts, and the contrariety of the Goſpel to their former courſe of life, forbidding the leaſt Impurity, and threatening vengeance againſt the ſmalleſt ſin which they poor wretches were wholy immerſed in; and in honour of their Gods, were not onely taught to practiſe, but comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to obſerve.</p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding ſuch great contradictions, the Goſpel of Chriſt, which is <hi>the power of God to ſalvation,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained both Jews and Gentiles with a holy violence to break aſunder their unlawful Oaths, to diſclaim their former Religions, to flie from the ſnares and deluſions of the Devil, and to become Proſelytes to the Religion of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>For when that glorious Light the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the World, the beams of his Majeſty were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately diſperſed over the face of the Earth, and his Glory in a ſhort time diſpelled that hideous darkneſs which had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread the World, and <hi>brought Life and Immortality to light.</hi> For ſo the Evangeliſt tells us, that by the miraculous inſtinct and conduct of a Star, the news of his birth was revealed to the furthermoſt parts of the Earth, as ſoon as ever he was born; and the Princes thereof came to pay their Adoration to him, and when they ſaw him, <hi>fell down and worſhipped him,</hi> Mat. 2. And when he entered upon his Prophetick Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, though he <hi>did not cry, nor lift up, nor cauſe his voice to be heard in the ſtreets,</hi> yet the Children of men ſlockt in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to hear him, deſervedly counting it their greateſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to become the Diſciples of ſo glorious a Maſter. So great Worth they ſaw in his Perſon, and ſuch Excellency in his Doctrine; ſuch glorious Rewards he propounded to them, &amp; ſuch intolerable miſeries he warn'd them to flie from, that they made haſt to deliver themſelves from the bonds of ſin, by which they were detained Captives to the will of the Devil, and without delay became the Followers of Chriſt, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying in nothing more, than in being Chriſtians.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:45644:16"/>
            <p>And as our Lord himſelf did ſo miraculouſly reſcue the Souls of men from their ſubjection to Sin and Satan, ſo that life and vigour which continually attends the diſpenſation of the Goſpel, hath been illuſtriouſly manifeſt in oppoſition to all the Powers of Darkneſs, and the Malice of Hell it ſelf. For as his Apoſtles went up and down preaching the Goſpel, the Lord <hi>added to the Church dayly ſuch as ſhould be ſaved:</hi> Three thouſand Souls became Converts to the Chriſtian Faith at one Sermon of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. In the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire and the Province of <hi>Judea,</hi> multitudes, multitudes thron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the Kingdom of Chriſt; and not onely the weak and impotent people, but the great ones, and wiſe men of the Earth, cheerfully embraced this divine Religion, accounting their Strength weakneſs, and their Wiſdom folly, until then. <hi>Cornelius</hi> a Centurion became a Proſelyte to it; <hi>Nero</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily had ſome Saints; <hi>Sergius Paulus</hi> a Proconſul, and <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the famous <hi>Areopagite</hi> at <hi>Athens,</hi> became Converts to the Chriſtian Faith. And the Hiſtories of the Church preſent us with many and many excellent Perſons of great eſteem for their admirable Learning, and vaſt Endowments, who in a ſhort ſpace of time voluntarily forſook the Pomps and Vanities of this wicked World, and ſincerely devoting themſelves to the ſervice of Chriſt, were deſervedly famous in their Generations for Piety and Devotions. Which very Argument <hi>Arnobius</hi> inſiſts upon when he reaſoned with the Heathen to perſwade them to receive the Faith of Chriſt; that men of the greateſt Wits and Parts,<note place="margin">Tam mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Ingeniis paediti O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratores, Grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci, Rhetores Conſulti Juris ac Medici, Philoſophie etiam ſecreta rimantes Magiſteria hec expetunt, ſpretis quibus paulò antè fidebant, &amp;c. <hi>Arnob. cont. Gent. l. 2. p. 44.</hi>
               </note> Orators, Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Rhetoricians, Lawyers, Phyſitians, and Philoſophers, forſook their former Sentiments, and adhered to the Doctrine of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Nay, <hi>ſo mightily prevailed the Word of God,</hi> in deſpight of the Devil and all the Powers of Darkneſs, that within an Age
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45644:16"/>or two after the Incarnation of the Son of God, his dominion was as large as the World, and extended over the Territories of the whole Earth. <hi>Heſterni ſumus,<note place="margin">Apol. C. 36. c. 1.</note> &amp; veſtra omnia implevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> For the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was utterly deſtroyed, and the <hi>daily Sacrifice</hi> perfectly <hi>ceaſed:</hi> and ſuch the Reformation in the Gentile World, that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils forſook their ancient Habitations, and trembled,<note place="margin">Euſ. Ecc. Hiſt. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3. l. 3. c. 8.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the noiſe of the Goſpel ſounded; their clamorous Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles ſoon became dumb, and their principal Deities mute as a Child; their great Gods forſook their beloved Temples; and though ſome were chained, yet they were conſtrained to run away.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſo bold and confident were the Primitive Chriſtians in their Apologies before their Perſecutors, that they chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged the Governours and Rulers,<note place="margin">Tert. Apol. c. 23, 22.</note> before whom they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, to bring any perſons poſſeſſed with evil Spirits, or grieved with any other Infirmities, and if they did not in the Name of Chriſt reſtore the one ſound to his health, &amp; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to an entire mind, they would be content to die the moſt ignominious accurſed death. Nay,<note place="margin">Lact. de falſ. Sap. l. 2. c. 25, 26</note> to diſcover the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and vertue of the Chriſtian Religion, they were bold to ſay, that by the Adminiſtration of the Goſpel they would undertake to convince the moſt obſtinate, to convert the moſt obdurate ſinner, and to transform the moſt diabolical and helliſh nature into a divine and heavenly temper; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying hereby thoſe lofty Expreſſions of the Apoſtle, that <hi>the Word of God is quick and powerful, and ſharper than any two-edged ſword,</hi> Heb. 4.12. <hi>Mighty through God, to the pulling down of ſtrong holds, caſting down imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth itſelf againſt the knowledge of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.4, 5.</p>
            <p>And to this very day the Son of God hath rode in triumph over the Devil, not onely by <hi>teaching men to deny all ungoali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and worldly luſts, to live ſoverly, righteouſly, and godly in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45644:17"/>this preſent world;</hi> but by <hi>redeeming them</hi> actually <hi>from all iniquity, and purifying to himſelf a peculiar people zealous of good works.</hi> Thus it was propheſied of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> Iſai. 61.1. and fulfilled by him when he appeared in the World, as he himſelf teſtifies: <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord is upon me, becauſe he hath appointed me to preach the Goſpel to the poor; he hath ſent me to heal the broken-hearted, to preach deliverance to the captives, and recovering of ſight to the blind; to ſet at liberty them that are bound, and to preach the acceptable year of the Lord,</hi> Luke 4.18, 19. In a word, the glorious company of the Apoſtles, the goodly fellowſhip of the Prophets, the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Army of Martyrs, and all the Saints of God that have departed this life in his Faith and Fear, and now make up that part of the Church Triumphant in the Kingdom of Heaven, waiting for the accompliſhment of our Victory, and the perfecting of the Body of Chriſt, have been redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Bloud of the Son of God, delivered by him from the ſnares of Death and the power of the Devil, and are now ſate down with the Lamb of God in the higheſt Heavens.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Son of God will moſt certainly obtain a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Victory over the Devil, before he reſigne up his Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſion to his Father; as from all eternity he was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordained, and in the fulneſs of time ſolemnly inaugurated into this Office. As to this very day he hath been faithful in the adminiſtration of it to the deſtruction of Satan's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; ſo he will undoubtedly continue till he hath accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed the number of his Elect,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.28.</note> compleated the body of the Church Triumphant, and ſubdued the Power and Authority of his Enemies. So that though the Devil diſturb the Peace of the Church, and make his rendezvouz in the World, <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king whom he might devour</hi> and deſtroy; yet the Son of God, who in his Reſurrection <hi>led captivity captive,</hi> and to this day hath <hi>gone on conquering and to conquer,</hi> will ſtill proceed in this victorious manner, till he hath perfectly routed the Devil and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45644:17"/>his Angels, and his place be found no more on the Earth, as it is propheſied by St. <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 12. For at the laſt and dreadful day, there ſhall be a general conflagration in the World, to conſume the Wickedneſs thereof; when the Devil and his Angels ſhall be conſtrained to appear before this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Prince, and receive their final doom which was denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced upon them when they were caſt out of Heaven, to be thruſt into the bottomleſs Pit with all their accurſed Crew, to be <hi>tormented day and night,</hi> and to <hi>dwell in everlaſting burnings;</hi> when the great Redeemer of the World, the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of mans Salvation, ſhall gloriouſly aſcend to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Father, and in triumphant Chariots carry up with him an innumerable company of bleſſed Saints, who ſhall ſit down with him in his Fathers Kingdom, and reign as Kings and Queens for evermore.</p>
            <p>We have hitherto conſidered the truth of the Propoſition delivered in the Text, That it was the grand deſigne and purpoſe of the Son of God to deſtroy the works of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; that he was manifeſt in the World to deliver Man from his Power and Dominion; to teach and enable them to walk in the ways of Vertue and Goodneſs. From which Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 'tis juſt and obvious to infer three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From hence men may learn whether they be indeed the Servants of God, and Diſciples of Chriſt; or the Slaves and Vaſſals of the Devil. 'Tis the continual Employment of that accurſed Spirit, to lay Snares in our way to Heaven, to tempt and entice Souls to the practice of ſin, and thereby to aſcertain their eternal Ruine: On the other ſide, 'tis the conſtant endeavour of our bleſſed Saviour, to deliver men from their evil ways, to encline their hearts to the Love, and their lives to the Practice of all manner of Goodneſs; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to reconcile them unto God, and to ſave them in the day of the Lord. Flatter not your ſelves then in a buſineſs of ſo great concernment. Our Apoſtle lays down a plain Rule from this Doctrine: <hi>He that doth righteouſneſs, is righteous, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45644:18"/>as</hi> Chriſt <hi>is righteous</hi> v. 7. <hi>He that committeth ſin, is of the Devil,</hi> v. 8. <hi>Whoſoever is born of God, doth not commit ſin,</hi> v. 9. And, <hi>in this the children of God are manifeſt, and the children of the Devil; whoſoever doth not righteouſneſs, is not of God,</hi> v. 10. Let men pretend what they will, a ſinful and wicked life is a plain Mark and Character of one that belongs to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: as on the contrary, a vertuous and godly Converſation is the onely ſigne of a Child of Grace, the onely certain evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of a good Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>That man who in the general courſe of his life carries a ſincere reſpect to the Commandments of God, and in good earneſt ſtudies to conform his actions to his holy Laws; that carefully avoids the occaſions of evil, and ſeriouſly reſiſts the Wiles and Temptations of the Devil; that deſpiſeth not any Precept of the Goſpel, becauſe the matter of it may ſeem ſmall and inconſiderable; nor refuſeth the ſevereſt duty, becauſe of the pains and trouble it may put him to: Such a man is the honeſt upright Chriſtian, a true Diſciple and Sevant to the Son of God; notwithſtanding his infirmities and frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which through Inadvertency, Surprize, or a violent Temptation, he may ſometimes commit; which as 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for the beſt man in this imperfect State to ſecure and fortifie himſelf againſt, ſo the Mercies of God in the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the Goſpel, doth graciouſly pardon, and through the Merits of Chriſt, readily paſs them over.</p>
            <p>But <hi>he that committeth ſin, is of the Devil;</hi> He that caſts off the fear of God from his eyes, and lives in a conſtant courſe of a wicked life; that complies with the Temptations of the Devil, but is careleſs and indifferent in the Profeſſion and Practice of Religion; that habituates himſelf to the practice of any one known ſin, or the neglect of any neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Chriſtian duty; though he be not arrived to the highth of wickedneſs, but make ſome ſhew and appearance of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by proſeſſing the Chriſtian Faith, frequenting the publick Offices of Religion, and exerciſing the material parts
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45644:18"/>of ſome Vertues and Graces; yet if his Obedience be not uniform and entire according to the ſcope and tenour of the Goſpel, he is certainly in a ſtate of ſin and iniquity; and whatever his Profeſſion or Confidence be, without contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie a Child of the Devil: for St. <hi>James</hi> tells us, that true Chriſtian Wiſdom muſt ſhew itſelf <hi>without partiality without hypocriſie:</hi> and the ſame Apoſtle confidently aſſures us, that <hi>whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, is guilty of all.</hi> Jam. 3.18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 2.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Argument is an excellent <hi>Criterion</hi> to judge of the truth of Doctrines, which are delivered as the Doctrines of Chriſt, <hi>whether they be ſo or no.</hi> Our Apoſtle gives us an admonition and direction to this purpoſe, 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. <hi>Beloved, believe not every Spirit, but try the Spirits, whether they be of God. Every Spirit that confeſſeth that Jeſus is come in the fleſh;</hi> that is, every Doctrine which is conſonant with the Incarnation of the Son of God, and the deſign of his being manifeſt in the world, <hi>is of God;</hi> for <hi>God manifeſted in the fleſh, is a great Myſtery of Godlineſs,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.15. and St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the Chriſtian Faith, <hi>the truth which is after God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> Tit. 1.1.</p>
            <p>But <hi>every Spirit that confeſſeth not that Jeſus is come in the fleſh;</hi> that is, every Doctrine which is contrary to the deſign of his Incarnation, that is apt to hinder a good life, or invalidate the neceſſity of it, cannot be from God. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Doctrine gives licence or connivance to ſin, muſt needs proceed from the Devil, that enemy of all goodneſs, though the Author pretend to an Infallible Spirit, like the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> or to Divine Inſpiration, like our Modern Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſts.</p>
            <p>Yet in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſuch Doctrines as theſe are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly conſtituted, as Eſſential parts of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and impoſed upon the Chriſtian world, with the ſame authority, as the moſt Fundamental Articles of the Chriſtian Faith: Thus the Sacrament of Penance, joyned
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45644:19"/>with Confeſſion, is repreſented as ſufficient to Salvation; The Doctrine of Purgatory, which ſuppoſeth an expiation of ſin (by the Prayers of the living) after death: Prayers in an unknown Tongue: The prohibition of the Scriptures without licence to the people: The diſpenſing of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences; the Popes Supremacy and Infallibility; and others of the ſame nature, are impoſed with the ſame Authority, and received with the ſame Veneration and Piety, as the belief of Deity, the Redemption of the world by the Son of God, and the Rewards of another Life. It's need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and would be too tedious, to conſider them particularly; but what man of common ſenſe and underſtanding, is not able to ſee, that theſe Doctrines are directly, and of their own nature, great impediments and obſtructions of a good life, and therefore are not of God?</p>
            <p>To the ſame ill purpoſe tend thoſe frequent diſcourſes of the Abſolute Decrees of God, the irreſiſtibility of Divine Grace, together with the weak and imperfect deſcription of Faith, with the ſtrange Metaphorical expreſſions by which thoſe Doctrines are unhappily repreſented to the world; with Doctrines of like affinity confidently vented and ſpread abroad by the too curious and bold diſcoverers of hidden and unrevealed Myſteries. For that Faith that doth not ingage men to become new Creatures, and to keep the Commandments of God, can never juſtifie, much leſs ſave them; and that Grace which ſhall infallibly work to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert men, however diſpoſed, may make men careleſs and oſcitant to the duties of Religion, but doth neither require nor incourage their care and induſtry; and thoſe decrees which have irrevocably and abſolutely ſentenced men to Heaven or Hell from all Eternity, may pamper ſome with preſumption, drive others to deſpair, but can have no effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy to perſwade men to <hi>work out their Salvation with fear and trembling.</hi> And therefore thoſe perſons that have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibed theſe opinions, ought to have a great care to keep their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45644:19"/>Hearts ſounder than their Heads; that they may be good, though they apprehend no rational neceſſity why they ſhould be ſo. But if ſuch men be good upon falſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Principles, (as I make no queſtion but many ſuch erroneous perſons are) what eminent Lights might they be in the Church of God, for ſanctity and holineſs of life, if they would ſuffer right Reaſon, and the acknowledged Principles of Religion to ſupplant their Erroneous Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and be perſwaded to embrace <hi>the truth as it is in Jeſus!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, the conſideration of this Doctrine ſhould be a prevalent and moſt effectual Argument to perſwade thoſe that believe the truth and purport of it, to leave off their ſins, and to lead Religious and godly lives. We acknowledge our ſelves Chriſtians, and thereby profeſs to believe the Doctrine of Chriſt, to live in obedience to his commands, and in the ſtricter imitation of his holy life: let us then <hi>look unto Jeſus, the Captain of our Salvation,</hi> that we may proſecute that great and glorious end, for which he came into the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Emmanuel,</hi> God with, and incarnate among us. That he was <hi>manifeſt in the fleſh to deſtroy the works of the devil,</hi> hath been in ſome meaſure repreſented to your conſideration, both from his holy life, and meritorious death, the deſign and tendency of his Doctrine, the miſſion and diſpenſation of the Holy Ghoſt, the many ſignal and eminent victories over the Devil throughout the world, in reſcuing many Souls from the tyranny of the Devil, and the powers of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and giving them <hi>power to become the Sons of God.</hi> You there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that call your ſelves by that worthy name of <hi>Chriſtians, conſider the high Prieſt of your profeſſion,</hi> and the great obligation that lies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you to <hi>walk worthy of your calling, and to live as becomes the Goſpel,</hi> by renouncing the Devil and all his works, the pomps and vanities of this wicked world, and all the ſinful luſts of the fleſh; that as you profeſs to believe the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, ye may keep Gods holy will and Commandments all the days of your life: That <hi>having eſcaped the corruption that is in the world through luſt,</hi> ye may be <hi>partakers of the Divine Nature;</hi> and as the Apoſtle exhorts, <hi>give all diligence to add to your faith vertue, and to vertue knowledge, and to knowledge temperance, and to temperance patience, and to patience god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and to godlineſs brotherly kindneſs, and to brotherly kindneſs cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and that <hi>theſe things may be in you and abound:</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. &amp;c.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45644:20"/>This our Baptiſmal Covenant obligeth us to; this the Sacrament of the Lords Supper would enable us to effect; this the principles of our Chriſtian profeſſion require; this the precepts of our moſt holy Religion commands; for this the bleſſed promiſe of Gods Grace is tendered to Mankind in the diſpenſation of the Goſpel; this the bleſſed hope of Eternal Glory ſhould incourage us to, and the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful apprehenſion of everlaſting damnation ſhould make us afraid to neglect.</p>
            <p>And if hitherto we have been ſo deſperately mad, to continue in ſlavery and ſubjection to the Devil, and thereby to ſtand at open de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance, and direct hoſtility with the Son of God: Let us not perſiſt a moment longer in ſo wretched, ſo miſerable a condition; but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately break off our League with Satan, and become the ſervants and worſhippers of <hi>the only true God, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, whom he hath ſent.</hi> For though our caſe be very bad, whilſt inſlaved to the Tyranny of the Devil; yet ſince we enjoy the Goſpel, that word of Everlaſting life; no man ought to conclude, that his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is deſperate. <hi>For now is the accepted time, now is the day of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.2. <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave the chiefeſt of ſinners,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. So that the Son of God is willing to <hi>ſave us from our ſins,</hi> and the malice of the Devil too, if we be willing to <hi>leave off our ſins,</hi> and to <hi>ſerve him in holineſs and righteouſneſs:</hi> we may yet be <hi>turned from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan unto God,</hi> and ſo be reſcued from the ſlavery of the Devil and our luſts, <hi>into the glorious liberty of the Sons of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But at this time eſpecially, in which we are to Commemorate the Incarnation of the Son of God, who came to viſit us in great hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and in infinite mercy to deliver us from the power of the Devil, we ſhould ſeriouſly reſolve to baniſh ſin from our hearts and lives, that the Son of God may take poſſeſſion of our Souls; and <hi>dwelling in our Spirits by Faith,</hi> we may bring forth the fruits of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Charity, and all other Chriſtian Vertues and Graces, to the praiſe and honour of his bleſſed Name; that in the laſt day, when he ſhall come again in his glorious Majeſty to judge both the quick and the dead, we may riſe to the life immortal, through him who liveth and raigneth, with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, now and for ever. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
